<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Moses and Iethro: or the good magistrate containing sundry necessary admonitions to all maiors, gouernours, and freemen of townes corporate, as they were deliuered in a sermon at S. Maries in Douer on the election day. By Io: Reading.</title>
            <author>Reading, John, 1588-1667.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1626</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 43 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10515</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20791</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115680</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850898</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850898</idno>
            <idno type="VID">16134</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10515)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 16134)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1151:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Moses and Iethro: or the good magistrate containing sundry necessary admonitions to all maiors, gouernours, and freemen of townes corporate, as they were deliuered in a sermon at S. Maries in Douer on the election day. By Io: Reading.</title>
                  <author>Reading, John, 1588-1667.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Legatt for Robert Allott, and are to be sold in Pauls-Church-yard at the signe of the Gray-hound,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1626.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:16134:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>MOSES AND IETHRO: Or the Good Magiſtrate:</p>
            <p>Containing ſundry neceſſary ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monitions to all <hi>Maiors, Gouernours,</hi> and <hi>Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> of Townes Corporate, as they were deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered in a Sermon at S. <hi>Maries</hi> in <hi>Douer</hi> on the Election Day.</p>
            <p>By IO: READING.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2 CHRON. 19.6, &amp;c.</hi>
               </bibl> Take heede what yee doe: for yee execute not the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of man, but of the Lord, and <hi>he will be</hi> with you in the cauſe and iudgements.</q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>Iohn Legatt</hi> for <hi>Robert Allott,</hi> and are to be ſold in <hi>Pauls</hi>-Church-yard at the ſigne of the <hi>Gray-hound.</hi> 1626.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:16134:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16134:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Worſhipfull the <hi>Maior</hi> and <hi>Iurats</hi> of <hi>Douer:</hi> To the <hi>Maiors, Barons,</hi> and <hi>Free-men</hi> of the <hi>Cinqueports:</hi> Grace and peace be multiplied in <hi>Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
               </hi> Haue tendered theſe Meditations to your ſo generall Patronage, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you all haue one intereſt in them; In as much as you all make one bodie. I am not ignorant, that they are neither accommodated to the excellencie of theſe times, nor the curioſitie of ſuch as will not abide wholeſome Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine; I doe know, that (to guiltie conſciences, and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall mindes of men not ſo much propoſing to themſelues reformation, as formalitie in hearing) all plaine and home-put reproofes are like acrimonie of medicines to greene wounds: I remember that truth, by reaſon of our corrupt will and peruerſe affections, is fruitfull in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getting enemies; neither am I to learne this out of mine owne particulars; it was euer ſo with the Prophets, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, Martyrs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yea and Christ himſelfe: yet haue I (without care, what the vnreformable ſhall thinke, or ſay of my plaine dealing) addreſſed theſe exhortations to thoſe few of many amongst you, who (duely conſidering how heauily it importeth vs to admoniſh ſinners,<note place="margin">Ezek. 3.20.</note> leſt their blood be required at our hands, to cry aloud and ſpare not, to ſhew the people their tranſgreſsions,<note place="margin">I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 8.1.</note> and the houſe
<pb facs="tcp:16134:3"/>of <hi>Iacob</hi> their ſinnes) will not therefore thinke we are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come their enemies, becauſe we tell them the trueth, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member how neceſſary the greatest instancie, and roundest warnings now are in theſe dangerous times, wherein the dreadfull hand of God, hath in our late viſitations, po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted out the neglect, conniuence, and impunitie, begetting that curſed libertie of ſinning, for which the wrath of God commeth on the children of diſobedience: and, that (ſince we must all indifferently appeare before the tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall of Christ) they are not friends,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Cor. 5.10.</note> who paſſe by our vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regarded faults, as the Prieſt and Leuite by the wounded man, but they who like the good <hi>Samaritan,</hi> powre in Wine and Oyle, to clenſe and heale, and conſequently to prepare vs againſt the ſtrict examination of the moſt holy Iudge: Conſider therefore what I ſay, and the Lord God giue you vnderſtanding in all things, that vpon a preſent reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the Lord may make fast the barres of our gates, turne his indignation from vs, and ſet the cloudy pillar, day and night, betwixt vs and our inſolent enemies: in which hope I rest</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours to loue, and ſerue you. IO: READING.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:16134:3"/>
            <head>Moſes <hi>and</hi> Jethro.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Exod. 18.24.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>And Moſes harkened vnto the voice of his father in law, and did all that he had ſayd.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Oſes</hi> doth here paſſe to the hiſtorie of a new policy which thenceforth hee obſerued: there are two parts of it; the firſt declareth the aduice and counſell of <hi>Iethro,</hi> gluing being and life to this politicall courſe: From the 17. verſe, to the 23. the ſecond relateth the execution of the ſame counſell from the 24. verſe.</p>
            <p>In the firſt is found an <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, an euerſion, reiection<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or reproouing their former cuſtome, <hi>the thing which thou doest is not well:</hi> as if one ſhould tell you, you haue ſome inconueniences in your cuſtome,<note place="margin">Verſ. 17.</note> which are neither right, nor good: ſo found <hi>Iethro</hi> ſome ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſect or reformation in the cuſtomes of <hi>Moſes</hi> and the republicke of Iſrael.</p>
            <p>In the ſecond is a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or propoſition of an order from that time to be inſtituted.</p>
            <p>Concerning the perſons eligible to the magiſtracy, theſe particulars are ſet downe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Quis praefecturus eſſet. Moſes, conſulta ſacie Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini, Be thou for the people to God-ward,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſ. 19.</note> 
               <hi>and report thou the cauſes vnto God, and admoniſh them of the ordinance and of the lawes, &amp;c.</hi> that is,<note place="margin">Verſ. 22.</note> iudge thou in difficult
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:16134:4"/>cauſes, which cannot be decided, but by conſulting with God.</p>
            <p n="2">2, <hi>Quos eligeret:</hi> prouide among all the people <hi>men of courage, fearing God, men dealing truely, hating couetouſneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3, <hi>Quibus, Appoint</hi> ſuch ouer them to bee rulers <hi>ouer thouſands, rulers ouer hundreds, rulers ouer fifties, and rulers ouer tens:</hi> Let them iudge the people at all ſeaſons—that is for the manner of iudicature which is ſet downe, verſ. 22. the euent is promiſed, verſ. 23. if thou <hi>doe this thing (and God ſo commaund thee</hi>) both thou ſhalt be able to endure, and all this people ſhall alſo goe quietly to their place. Immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately after the aduice, commeth the narration of the fact the fruit and iſſue thereof. <hi>Moſes</hi> obtemperated, <hi>And Moſes harkened vnto the voice of his father in law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The words co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine <hi>Moſes</hi> his
<list>
                  <item>1. Regularitie, and diſpoſition in ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king counſell, <hi>And Moſes harkened vnto, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. Conformitie, in the execution thereof, <hi>and he did all, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And Moſes harkened vnto the voice of his father in law:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. His regula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titie. Gen. 3.17.</note> Hearing is the ſenſe of diſcipline: errour firſt entred into the ſoule through that dore, the woman harkened to the ſerpent and was ſeduced, and becauſe the man hearkened to the voice of his wife, in that which God forbad, he was curſed, and the cure muſt follow the euill, the ſame was into the ſoule, we muſt be healed through the care: there the word entreth to beget ſauing <hi>faith, faith is by hearing:</hi> there coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell entreth into the mind,<note place="margin">Rom. 10.17. Pro 2.2.10, 11, 12.</note> to make men wiſe; cauſe <hi>thine cares to hearken vnto wiſedome, encline thine heart
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:16134:4"/>to vnderstanding:</hi> when <hi>wiſedome entreth into thine heart, and knowledge delighteth thy ſoule, then ſhall counſell preſerue thee; and vnderſtanding ſhall keep thee, and deliuer thee from the euill way</hi> —.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Moſes</hi> was here ruled by his father in lawes counſel: what that was, the precedent ſtory hath, and I ſhall ſpeake ſummarily of it in the conclusion hereof.</p>
            <p>For the preſent I haue to obſerue the regularitie and diſpoſition of conſidering him in relation to his counſeller: <hi>Moſes</hi> had heard God ſpeake: had receiued commiſſion, and inſtruction from God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe; God had by his hands done wonderfull things in the land of Egypt, wonders in the ſea,<note place="margin">Num. 14.14.</note> wonders in the deſert; the Lord was among that people, he went before them <hi>by day time in a pillar of a cloud, and in a pillar of fire by night,</hi> to giue them light;<note place="margin">Exod. 13.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Deut. 1.31.33.</note> and to ſearch them out a place to pitch their tents in: this was the dreadfull ſtandard of the Lord of hoſtes, where God ſet it downe, they pitched their tents, when he remoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued it, they were to march againe. The Lord did beare them in the wilderneſſe, <hi>at a man doth beare his ſonne:</hi> The Lord had promiſed <hi>Moſes</hi> his aſſiſtance,<note place="margin">Deut. 1.31. Exod. 3.12.</note> 
               <hi>certainly I will be with thee,</hi> to dictate what he ſhould ſpeake in his ſeruice,<note place="margin">Exod. 1.12 15</note> 
               <hi>I will be with thy mouthy, and will teach thee what thou ſhalt ſay,</hi> and to direct in all caſes of deliberation, <hi>I will teach you what yee ought to doe:</hi> and leſt <hi>Moſes</hi> ſhould ſtill diſtruſt his own ability<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> God confirmeth his promiſes by miracles peculiar to <hi>Moſes</hi> ſenſe. Thus was <hi>Moſes</hi> enabled by the ſpirit of coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell: but as for <hi>Iethro,</hi> whether hee were Prince,<note place="margin">Exod. 4.</note> or Prieſt of <hi>Midian,</hi> or both. I diſpute not: it was an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient manner among the nations, for Kings to bee ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificers;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ariſtot. Polis.</hi> 3.10</note> and though <hi>Dauids</hi> ſonnes are called <hi>Cohens,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Sam. 8.18.</note>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:16134:5"/>which is interpreted,. <hi>Chron.</hi> 18.17. <hi>Primi ad manum regis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal 1 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0 4. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 3. P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>l. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>2.9. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>r 32.32.</note> chiefe about the king: yet the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> doth v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſually import, the ſame which is in Greek, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (which the Apoſtle vſeth <hi>Hebr.</hi> 7.) ſo called of ſacrificing, and doing of ſacred workes: admit he were a Prince, yet in this new forme of a trauelling common-wealth, (which could borrow neither modell, nor rules, from any other ſtate then in being, but was immediately dependent, for lawes, policies, and gouernment, on the word and commandement of God) hee could not be acquainted with any ſuch myſteries of ſtate, as might ſerue to declare him a fit counſeller for an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne gouernment: yet <hi>Moſes</hi> hearkened vnto his voice. How abundance of knowledge (eſpecially at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by immediate reuelation) puffeth vp, the meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger of Sathan buffeting <hi>Paul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 12.</note> to preuent that miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe, doth ſufficiently declare: how authority great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the mind, <hi>Pauls</hi> preſcription to <hi>Timothy</hi> may ſerue to intimate, a biſhop (ſaith he) <hi>may not be a yong ſcholler,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Tim. 3.6.</note> 
               <hi>leſt be being puffed vp, fall into the condemnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the diuell:</hi> he prohibited not his youth, as vnapt for that office:<note place="margin">1. Tim. 4.</note> let no man contemne thy youth, but the inexperience of ſuch a man as was <hi>nouiter inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus,</hi> and as it were <hi>nouella plantatio.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Chryſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>o<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> 10</note> The diuell doth mainely labour to bring men downe the ſame way by which himſelfe fell; therefore he tempteth the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant to preſumption, till ſuch a mind, like the riſing ſmoke,<note place="margin">Omnia vitia in male faclis ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend a ſunt, ſuperbia in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefactis, &amp;c. Aug. in Pſ. <hi>58 2 Cor. 12.10.</hi> Chryſ. ib. hom. <hi>26.</hi>
               </note> by greatning it ſelfe, vaniſh and come to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. He tempteth the learned, and good, to pride, and contempt of others, therefore when all vices els are to be feared in euill workes, pride onely is to be feared in good. When <hi>I am weake then am I ſtrong</hi> (ſaid the Apoſtle) <hi>Vbi afflictio, ibi &amp; conſolatio,</hi> where
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:16134:5"/>affliction is, there is conſolation, and that grace which fortifieth with humility, by ſubduing, and leſſening the mind, which in the naturall man hath for the moſt part, ſuch dependance on things externall, that the mind of man and his condition, like the beaſts and the wheeles in <hi>Ezekiels</hi> viſion, are degreſſed,<note place="margin">Ezek. 1.10.</note> or lifted vp together, for that mind is on the outward eſtate which beareth it, as the ſpirit of the beaſts was in the wheeles. What ſo great a command as <hi>Moſes</hi> had might worke, they know, who becomming acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with ſuch titles of honor, ſuddainely forget them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, and their eares prooue nice and impatient of counſell. <hi>Saul</hi> did once thinke humbly of himſelfe, <hi>was little in his owne ſight;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Sam. 15.17.</note> then he would hearken to the aduice of <hi>Samuel,</hi> but being promoted to a king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, he neglected the voice of God : no doubt but there was a time when <hi>Rehoboam</hi> would haue heard the counſell of the ancient men, but feeling the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of a king in his hand, he reiected them for the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe of the young men: why go I ſo high, or farre? hath no man knowne, that a white ſtaffe hath in a yeere or two ſo inſpired an officer ouer a thouſand, that he could abide no aduiſe? <hi>Moſes</hi> in their language would haue ſaid: hath not God himſelfe put mine authority into my hand? hath hee not committed to my charge ſixe hundred thouſand men?<note place="margin">Num. 11.21.</note> haue I not talked with God in the mount? haue I not by the power of God confirmed my authority by ſundry miracles? or in the language of the willfull <hi>Sodomites,</hi> ſome would haue replyed, <hi>he is come alone as a stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and ſhall he iudge and rule?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 19.9.</note> or as the inſolent <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſes</hi> to the yong man whoſe eyes Chriſt had opened, <hi>thou art altogether borne in ſinnes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 9.34.</note> 
               <hi>and doest thou teach
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:16134:6"/>vs?</hi> thou art not acquainted with the affaires of this new ſtate: content thy ſelfe with thy charge at <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian:</hi> But this meekeſt ſeruant of God for all thoſe glorious dignities conferred on him, hearkened to his counſell, who was farre inferiour to himſelfe: lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing vs in his example this inſtruction.</p>
            <p>The beſt and moſt excellent men wil hearken to the aduice of others, yea, ſometimes of their inferiours: for,</p>
            <p n="1">1. The wiſeſt men are ſubiect to ouer-ſights and er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours: neuer to erre is peculiar to God alone who onely is omniſcient, who therefore hath beene his counſeller? but he giueth not all knowledge to the wiſeſt, to humble them who being ſubiect to a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand errours, are yet apt to be proud with a falſe opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of wiſedome.</p>
            <p n="2">2. God doth ſometimes reueale wiſedome and counſell to men whoſe aſpects are not promiſing, whoſe condition is meane, and obſcure, (there was found in the little City <hi>a poore wiſe man, who deliuered the city by his wiſedome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccl. 9.14.15</note> though he were ſo little reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, that <hi>no man remembred him</hi>) and hide it from the learned and prudent, as to aſcertaine men, that himſelfe is the authour and fountaine of euery perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction ſo to teach them, that they ought not to bee ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogant of that they haue receiued, ſince the ſimple may eft-ſoone controule their proiections, neither to contemne others to whom God will ſometimes make them beholding for aduice.</p>
            <p>Hence it commeth to paſſe that wiſe men loue coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, and fooles their owne waies: they know in the greateſt atchieuements counſel is better then ſtrength:<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>d.</note> they know it is a great miſery to want the aduice of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:16134:6"/>priuate friends, much greater is the want of counſell in matters publicke; they know aduice is a ſacred thing, they know that counſelleſſe force falleth with it owne weight:<note place="margin">Vis co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ij ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers mole ruit ſud. Caſsi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r. Ber<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, de conſid. l. <hi>4.</hi> c <hi>4.</hi> Ibid.</note> euery prouident man therefore <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilium quaerit:</hi> if it be not giuen him hee will purchaſe it. <hi>Bernard</hi> ſaith well, by counſell, <hi>tracta ante factum, quia poſt factum ſera retractatio eſt:</hi> aduiſe, before thou execute, repentance and counſell come too late, when things are done. Doe nothing without aduice, <hi>&amp; poſt factum non poenitebis:</hi> the reaſon why wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men loue others aduice, is becauſe ſeeing their owne wants, they ſuſpect, and are iealous of themſelues: the foole, becauſe he knoweth not ſo much as his owne defects, hath an high opinion of his own worth, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he is precipitate, and often vnlucky to himſelfe, or that vnhappy common-wealth committed to his managing: and like the <hi>Polypus</hi> (a true embleme of vnaduiſed men) taken in a ſnare,<note place="margin">Whoſe motto is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Ambroſ.</hi>
               </note> for want of taking heed. I conclude this point then. Counſell is for wiſe men, and correction for fooles, for theſe hate aduiſe: the wiſeſt of men hath the ſumme of all,<note place="margin">Prou. 12.15.</note> 
               <hi>The way of a foole is right in his owne eyes: but he that heareth coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell is wiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I know not yet to whom this addreſſe belongeth, but in the phraſe of <hi>Tamar</hi> I may ſay to him, <hi>Diſcerne I pray thee, cuius ſunt iſta, ſigillum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 38.25.</note> 
               <hi>ſudarium &amp; ſcipio iste.</hi>—I meane the ſeale and ſtaffe of office, to him I ſay, as this concerneth him, when the ſtaffe and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity ſhall be put into his hand by your ſuffrages, to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure him that he cannot be a good patriot who deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, and therefore will not hearken to counſell: ſo to you all I ſay, it firſt and for preſent concerneth you, who though many, are but one body, and in place of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:16134:7"/>one <hi>Moſes</hi> now to make choice, (one <hi>Moſes</hi> made choice of many Magiſtrates, you being many are to chooſe one) therefore your firſt part is in imitation of this man of God, to heare aduice what choice you ought to make: you muſt be <hi>auſcultantes:</hi> firſt to the Prophet, who by a laudable cuſtome, is to you as ſome <hi>Iethro,</hi> aduiſing you concerning your election: ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to thoſe graueſt, and moſt experienced members of your ſtate, whoſe age, imployment and obſeruation haue enabled them to iudge what man in reſpect of the particulars, fitteſt to be elected.</p>
            <p>The word is our cloudy pillar to direct our cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, when that remooueth we muſt follow it, when that ſtandeth,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Greg</hi> Math. 13. Mat. 13.16.</note> we muſt reſt: this is that <hi>cibus
mentis,</hi> in whoſe ſtrength we are to walke: this is that which maketh vs bleſſed in hearkning to it, and wiſe in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math. 7. 24.</hi> S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ultus verò haec audita diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>imulans, tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuper are<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam opus a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eationis im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penderi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, infide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liter flat, &amp;c. Hilar. Canon. <hi>6. Exod. 29.20.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>I will like him to a wiſe man, which hath builded his houſe on a rocke:</hi> hee and his worke ſhall ſtand. With this the good Magiſtrate muſt be initiated and conſecrated, (as the high Prieſts were wont to bee, with the blood of the ſacrifice: thou ſhalt take of the blood and <hi>put it vpon the tip of their right eare</hi>—<hi>and vpon the thumb of their right hand, and vpon the great toe of the right foot</hi>) their eare muſt firſt bee touched with the word, that it may be ſanctified and opened to counſell, next the hand, that their worke and admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration may be holy, and that their conuerſation may be blameleſſe.</p>
            <p>If this part be neglected, I eaſily beleeue the reſt will prooue vnhappy, and euil to you, what choice ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer you make: for how ſhall God giue you a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing in a good Magiſtrate, how ſhall hee proſper his beſt counſells, or endeauours to you, when to initiate
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:16134:7"/>him, you begin ſo euilly, as to contemne God? For he that deſpiſeth theſe things, deſpiſeth not man but God. And himſelfe faith againe,<note place="margin">Ezek. 3.7<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> 
               <hi>The houſe of Iſrael will not heare thee, for they will not heare me:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It muſt needs be euill likewiſe, where the aduice of men experienced, &amp; authoriſed to aſſiſt, is contemned.</p>
            <p>I ſay therefore, there are ſome men (I ſay not where, if it now concerne you, looke to it, if nor, lay it vp till it may) there are ſome men, for this cauſe moſt vnfit to be elected, becauſe they cannot abide the word of God, if it touch them, nor the counſell of good men, if it croſſe them. Some worldly men are like thoſe inhabitants by the falls of <hi>Nilus,</hi> the noiſe of other buſineſſes hath ſo filled their eares, that they cannot hearken: the Roman <hi>Peter</hi> hath cut off the right eare of ſome, and ſuch a <hi>Malcus</hi> heare no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſaue onely what the ſtate of Rome ſaith, there are no men to ſit at our helmes. Others are,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aug. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> Pſal. 57.</note> for other cauſes, deafe adders, who laying one eare to the earth, and couering the other with the tayle, (I mean, either for carnall aduice, or peruerſe affections luting vp their eares) cannot be drawne out of their holds: who louing their owne ignorance, cannot be brought out into the light with the moſt diuine and ſweet in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chantments of wiſedome:<note place="margin">ib. Aug.</note> theſe are not onely <hi>non au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dientes,</hi> men not hearkening, but <hi>omninò vt non vale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant audire facientes.</hi> So compoſing themſelues, that they may not heare theſe like the enraged Iewes when they heare their faults toucht, ſtop their eares, and flye vpon the ſpeaker. <hi>Non erant ſurdi, ſed fecerunt ſe ſurdos:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 7. <hi>Aug. qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſ.</hi>
               </note> they are thus affected alſo to the counſell of men, if it bee not a <hi>Miner<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a</hi> of their owne braine, pride and ſelfe-loue wil neither ſuffer then to execute,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:16134:8"/>nor apprehend it: there is nothing more intolerable then this out-ſides of a magiſtrate, who thinketh no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can be right but what himſelfe doth, or proie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cteth: looke neerer him, he admireth his owne head, talketh of the excellent ſeruices done to the ſtate, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parageth his predeceſſours, findeth inconveniences in other gouernments, in fine, as if hee were poſſeſſed with a ſpirit of contradiction, and his eares metamor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phoſed into tongues, hee who ſhould bee <hi>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſcultans</hi> with <hi>Moſes</hi> in my text is <hi>loquax,</hi> and nothing els, as for aduice he feareth it might import ſome weaknes in the receiuer to carry any but an independent brain. I haue ſhewed you the <hi>Idea</hi> and character of a Magiſtrate, whoſe example if any ſo euill be to be found, muſt be auoided: as <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſaid of <hi>Doctors,</hi> I muſt conclude of gouernours, <hi>Neminem bonum eſſe, &amp;c. qui non idem ſit docilis:</hi> he cannot be good who will not be taught: <hi>Moſes</hi> thought not himſelfe too good to be aduiſed by a man, who neuer went dry-foot through the red ſea, who neuer talked familiarly with God: to ſhut vp this point then; in your elections, it is ſafer, (I dare ſay it confidently) if you had any ſo vnhappy choice, to take a foole, who would performe this firſt part, and hearken to good counſell, then a wiſe man in his owne conceit; there is more hope of a foole then of him: a ſimple man with eares is better then a deafe <hi>Ahithephel</hi> with his moſt curious oracles: he then that hath an eare let him heare:<note place="margin">Tutiùs auditur veritas quàm pradicatur. Aug, de doct. Chriſt.</note> there is no feare in hearing good counſel, there is often danger in giuing it: <hi>Moſes hearkened vnto the voice of his father in law,</hi> this is the firſt part, the next is—</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2. His confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity in exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution.</note>
               <hi>He did all that he had ſaid.</hi> We are now arriued at the maine point, practiſe. It was the onely good diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:16134:8"/>poſition where we found him <hi>auſcultantem:</hi> hearing is the ſenſe of diſcipline, without this what euer is done were better vndone: without the eyes of coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell what is the ſtrongeſt will, but like ſome blind <hi>Sampſon</hi> pulling downe the pillars of a corporation. Yet we muſt not be <hi>Athenians</hi> giuen onely to heare,<note place="margin">Act. 17.</note> or tell: now commeth the fruit, in this ſame <hi>(fecit)</hi> without this, what euer is heard, were as good vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard: you ſee theſe are the <hi>gemelli,</hi> which, (as in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery happy ſtate they are borne together) cannot be diuided from the word of God, to the moſt godly counſell of man, there is a moſt neceſſary coniuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, of hearing, and doing: without the laſt wee can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bee iuſtified in the firſt, without the firſt, not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed in the laſt: many come to, and go from this place, without fruit; becauſe they come, <hi>vt audiant, non vt diſcant,</hi> not to learne, but to heare, either for faſhion, or for their pleaſures, as to a theater: ſo this place becommeth to them, for an houre, <hi>diuerſorium otii,</hi> and a conuenience of ſeeing and being ſeene. But except we he arken to the voice of God, wee cannot beleeue, faith is by hearing:<note place="margin">Rom. 10.</note> and except we doe what we heare, wee cannot be ſaued: not the hearers, but the doers of the law ſhall be iuſtified: ſo is it in morall affaires: the deafe man cannot be wiſe, but all coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, to a man, who will at laſt follow his owne fancy, is but loſt breath: ſuch aduiſers are but as <hi>Salomons</hi> graue Senators to his wilfull ſonne, heard, but not fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed.</p>
            <p>The ſumme of all is, if you will be well aduiſed, you muſt do all that is well ſaid to you; ſo did <hi>Moſes</hi> here, <hi>fecit quicquid dixerat.</hi> All, not ſome things onely, I neuer heard of any man either ſo peruerſe in his reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:16134:9"/>or ſingular in his opinion, but that hee would heare and doe ſome things to which he was aduiſed: but good counſell muſt be more vniuerſally followed, <hi>Moſes</hi> did all. There is a way to peruert the beſt coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, by ſeeming to follow it, as when wee leaue out that, in which is the life and efficacy of the whole: as if the clyent ſhould follow the preſcriptions of his learned counſell in all, except the maine point, as if, of ſundry dieticall rules of Phyſicke the patient ſhould diſpence with the principall: ſo <hi>Herod</hi> heard <hi>Iohn,</hi> and did many things, but not the maine: ſo <hi>Saul</hi> tooke <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muels</hi> counſell, for the <hi>Amaleck</hi> voyage, yet you ſee what became of it,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 15.</note> for ſparing <hi>Agag,</hi> &amp; the beſt of the ſpoile: ſo ſome pettie ſtatiſts vſe our miniſterie: ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times they will heare a ſermon before their elections, or aſſizes, and therin will heare, &amp; follow, as far as may make them ſeeme religious to a heedleſſe vulgar, as farre as the word complieth and agreeth with their deſires, but for this (all) it will neuer goe downe: for feare ignorance, or prophanes ſhould doe them the wrong to count them Puritans, who neuer loued ſo much as a ſhew of true holineſſe: and becauſe they ſuppoſe (that which can neuer be) that wiſedome may be ſeuered from religion, therefore they follow reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious counſel, but as <hi>Peter</hi> followed Chriſt to the high Prieſts hall, <hi>a farre off,</hi> and had rather forſweare any acquaintance with it,<note place="margin">Luk. 22.24.</note> then be outwardly diſaduanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by it: if ye will follow God as <hi>Moſes</hi> did <hi>Iethro's</hi> counſell, you muſt do all that he ſaith:</p>
            <p>Some may ſay, he that will hearken to euery body, ſhall bee like the chaffe toſſed to an fro with euery breath of wind: it is an endleſſe confuſion, a perplex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed torture to be troubled with the vnmannerly buz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zings
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:16134:9"/>of a many-headed vulgar, which oftentimes like thoſe troubleſome euening-flies<note n="*" place="margin">Blind Bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles.</note> caſt themſelues into our eares, with a great noiſe to no purpoſe. How irreſolute muſt he be, who will hearken to that varia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble maſter, ſounding of nothing more then contrarie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties? when ſhall he end his taske who vndertaketh to pleaſe euery body? where is that aduiſe, that deſigne, that vndertaking, which findeth no diſallowance? Adde to this, among many voices the ſerpent alſo hiſſeth; there are, who giue pernicious counſell. Shall I then hearken to all? I ſay not, take counſell of the euill, they who ſo do, are like thoſe who aske counſell of the dead, in which aduice commonly the diuell perſonateth the Prophet,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 28.7. &amp;c.</note> or of familiar ſpirits an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering in idols, as <hi>Ahaziah</hi> did; what neceſſity doth thus ſtraiten any man? <hi>Is it becauſe then is no God in Iſrael?</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Kin. 1.2.</note> hath he no ſeruants of whom thou maiſt take aduice? I ſay not, follow all that which ſeemeth coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell; the diuell ſaid, <hi>Command,</hi> or <hi>ſpeake, that theſe ſtones be made bread:</hi> it ſeemed charitable counſell,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> &amp;c.</note> but was a tentation. The young men ſaid to <hi>Rehoboam,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 4.3. 1. King. 12.10.</note> 
               <hi>Thus ſhalt thou ſay vnto this people</hi>—<hi>my least part ſhall be big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger then my fathers loynes.</hi> It was ſeducement, it was not counſell, both giuer and receiuer of ſuch aduice, are deceiued ſo often as they take al that which is ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken concerning counſell and deliberation to be good, <hi>Giue not thine heart to all the words that men ſpeake</hi> —thou muſt know thou art ſometimes amongſt the <hi>Sirens,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccl 7.23.</note> and muſt ſtop thine eares, for feare thou be drawne to death by them. But how ſhall I diſcerne which is counſell, and which ſeducement? Reduce all to theſe touch-ſtones, the word and will of God, and the commodity and good of them or him for whom
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:16134:10"/>ſuch counſell is intended: is it not agreeing with the holy will of God? bee it the oracles of <hi>Ahithophel,</hi> ſeeme it neuer ſo good for the ſtate, it is not to be fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed: there is no wiſedome, nor counſell againſt God: be it preiudicious to the ſtate, though for thine owne priuate gaine, ſeeme it neuer ſo good or pleaſing, it is a ſuggeſtion of treachery, it is no counſell which is taken for any ſubordinate reſpect againſt the ſtate, or the publike good which therein muſt be ſaued: is it againſt thy ſoules health, is it hurtfull to thy body, fame, eſtate, friends, directly or conſequently (wherein neither Gods honour, thy Prince, countrey, religion, or thy ſoule are otherwiſe intereſſed) it is ſeducement, it is not counſell: you ſee the meanes to diſcerne, and you muſt euer begin to weigh by this balance of the ſanctuary which ſtandeth before my text—<hi>if God ſo command thee</hi>—Some may ſay,<note place="margin">Verſe 33.</note> you haue your failings too, who deliuer the word: it is true we haue, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten preach the word in much weaknes, would God we were made perfect. I ſay not that the heathen ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges were more beneuolous hearers, then many Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, they wont to ſet the <hi>Graces</hi> by the ſtatue of <hi>Mercurie,</hi> to import that ſome ſlips of the ſpeakers of good things, are to be borne withall; but I ſay thoſe infirmities are not alwaies our proper faults, you alſo haue your ſhares in them, it is becauſe you want holy appetites to this word,<note place="margin">Nonnunquam vero propter auditoris cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pam ſubtrahi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur ſermo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctori: Greg. in
paſtor.</note> that God ſometimes and for your ſakes ſhortneth vs: when zealous and obedient hearers do hunger for the word, they do not only help the Preacher with their attention, but obtaine, that God, who fed multitudes with few loaues, enlargeth our hearts and openeth a dore of vtterance, yea ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times for holy hearers ſakes, the word is giuen plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:16134:10"/>euen to a <hi>Iudas,</hi> an euill teacher. To conclude this matter then, I muſt ſay in Chriſt his words, <hi>Take heede how you beare,</hi> and when you heare holy aduice, if God ſo command you, imitate this man of God in my text, who did all that <hi>Iethro</hi> had ſaid.</p>
            <p>What was that all? reade the 21. verſ. you ſhall quickly ſee the patterne of good Magiſtrates: 1. they muſt be <hi>men of courage, viros roboris,</hi> according to the Hebrew: what ſhould he doe with the ſword of iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice in his hand, who is of yong <hi>Iethers</hi> mettle,<note place="margin">Iudg. 8.20.</note> and dares not draw it to cut off maiefactors? acoward can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be either an honeſt man, or able Magiſtrate: for what counſell can rectifie that minde which dareth not be iuſt: feare is one of the deafe affections, no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons can maſter it. But becauſe all daring without the feare of God, is but temeritie and deſperate reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, this is annexed, they muſt bee <hi>ſuch as feare God:</hi> this is the only antidote againſt all baſe and ſeruile feare: he that truly feareth God, will not feare man, or be daunted, or diſcouraged from executing iuſtice. This feare of God, is the ground of all abilitie, it is the beginning of wiſdome; and all good order, &amp; gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, for thoſe who are truly holy cannot but labour to make others ſo: happie is that gouernment, where the Magiſtrate executeth his charge for conſcience ſake, doing his dutie, not like thoſe nigardly &amp; diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling votaries who will not offer without a witnes, but becauſe he knoweth that the eye of God is vpon him,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> &amp;c. Iſocr. orat. ad. Nic.</note> who indifferently hateth that man who iuſtifieth the wicked, and him who condemneth the iuſt. Think not then that it is the dutie proper &amp; peculiar to inferiors to liue wel, &amp; that the Magiſtrates may liue diſorderly:<note place="margin">— <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ib.</note> all the people looke on them, and from their actions,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:16134:11"/>deriue either honeſtie or libertie of ſinning: command thy ſelfe therefore thou that commandeſt others, and think it more honorable for thee, in the feare of God, to ſubdue and gouerne thine owne inordinate affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons then to exerciſe authoritie ouer thouſands of citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens: as much as thou art dignified aboue others, ſo much excell them in goodnes. This thou ſhalt doe, if thou feare God, and ſo conforme thy ſelfe to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of religious Gouernours, that thou mayſt be indifferently a patterne to thy inferiours and an emu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lator and imitator of thy ſuperiours.</p>
            <p>Thus muſt Magiſtrates be able men; they muſt alſo be men of power, vertue and actiuitie of body and minde, ſo the word is vſed. <hi>Gen.</hi> 47.6. and men of ſpirit and courage, ſo it is vſed. 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 26.6. that they may ſtand vp for the oppreſſed, as is ſaid of <hi>Moſes. Exo.</hi> 2.17.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Men dealing truly:</hi> or men of truth. The Greeke calleth them iuſt men: and <hi>Zach.</hi> 7.9. is mentioned <hi>iudgement of truth,</hi> ſo ſomtimes iuſtice goeth for truth, becauſe theſe vertues, are ſo neerely allyed: it is an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable connexion of theſe things, firſt of truth with courage and ſtrength of minde:<note place="margin">Veritas odio eſt. Tertul. apo. a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o. geat. c. <hi>14.</hi> Veritas odium
parit.</note> for truth cannot bee without enemies, it begetteth them: he had need to be a reſolued man who will be a man of truth: ſecondly, of truth &amp; the feare of God: for (ſaith <hi>Tertullian</hi>) truth knoweth ſhe is a ſtranger on earth, and that ſhe ſhal ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily finde enemies amongſt aliants:<note place="margin">Ib. Apol. c. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> yet that ſhe hath, her allies, manſion, hope, fauour, &amp; dignity in heauen. The Magiſtrate then muſt be a veritable, ſincere, and ſolid man, being what hee ſeemeth, and ſeeming ſuch an honourable patterne for others imitation, as the God of truth (whoſe vicegerents princes are) will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooue: he muſtloue and ſearch out the truth of cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:16134:11"/>(without which iuſtice cannot determine) not as <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſaith, of certaine Philoſophers, <hi>mimice affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctant veritatem, &amp; affectando corrumpunt:</hi> nor,<note place="margin">Ib. c. <hi>46.</hi>
               </note> as hee ſaith of the ſame, may he be <hi>furator eius &amp; cuſtos,</hi> both a theefe and keeper of truth. He muſt regard the truth and equitie of the cauſe, not friends, not kinred, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther relations, as if they might alter the caſe, or lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly peruert the courſe of iuſtice. The <hi>Thebans</hi> woont to make the ſtatues of Magiſtrates without hands, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting that they might be no takers; and the images of iudges without eyes, or with eyes ſhut, intimating that they ought truly and without reſpect of feare or fauour of any, impartially to giue ſentence; as it is ſaid of <hi>Seleucus,</hi> who would not againſt law, ſpare his ſons eyes, though out of his tender loue, to ſpare one of them, he put out one of his owne: ſo then you ſee they muſt be <hi>viriveritatis,</hi> not hypocrites in matter of iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, making a ſhew of doing it, but doing nothing leſſe. Some faile herein for feare, ſome for fauor, ſome for cuſtome ſake, others in their place woont to do ſo,<note place="margin">Veritatem ſe non conſuetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinem
cogno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minauit. Tertul. de Virg. veland. Conſuetudo ſine veritate, vetuflas erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris eſt. Cypr. ad Pomp. <hi>1. King. 21.8.</hi>
               </note> but it is a dangerous practiſe, for truth cannot be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed: Chriſt called himſelfe the truth, hee named not himſelfe cuſtome: cuſtome without truth or e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie is but the antiquity of error and iniquitie: ſome make their authoritie ſerue their owne ends, as when they execute law to ſatisfie priuate malice, or oppreſſe the innocent vnder ſome pretences of iuſtice or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatiue; ſo <hi>Iezabel</hi> vſed <hi>Ahabs</hi> ſeale: this is a frequent and vnhappie peruerting of equitie, the moſt hatefull hypocriſie in iudicature; when malice perſonateth iuſtice, when the diuell playeth the iudge.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Laſtly, they muſt be men <hi>hating couetouſneſſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith of Deacons to be elected, I muſt of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:16134:12"/>it behooueth them to bee men of good re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, (as it is <hi>Deut.</hi> 1.13. knowne men:) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, not <hi>deſirous of filthy lucre:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim 3.8. Deut. 16.19. 1 Sam 8.3. Prou. 1.19. Ezek. 22.27. Iſa. 56.11. <hi>Non ſit manu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> tua porrecta ad accipiendum, &amp; collecta ad dandum De modo benè vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vend. ſer.</hi> 44.</note>
the loue of gaine is the corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of iuſtice, and a reward putteth out the eye. I may ſay then to you, who are to be elected, as <hi>Bernard</hi> to one, let not thine hand be ſtretched out to take, and ſhut when it ſhould giue; and to you who are to make choice, as the ſame <hi>Bernard</hi> in another place, elect ſuch, <hi>as looke not into the hands, but neceſsities of the afflicted.</hi> It is a miſerable caſe when the Magiſtrate in a corporatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is ſo neceſſitous, that he hath too many temptious to be vniuſt: and it were to be wiſhed that in euery ſuch place, prouiſion might be made, that the elected Magiſtrate might be, for his eſtate, indepe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dent on the vulgar: for without this, rarely can iuſtice finde a due &amp; ſmoth courſe. The complaint is made, the nocent conuented, but the concluſion is too of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten (what euer ſhewes are made) the malefactor muſt be ſpared, becauſe he is, or may be a cuſtomer; then <hi>Eli</hi> ſaith onely,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 2.23.</note> 
               <hi>Why do ye ſuch things? for of all this peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple I heare euill reports of you,</hi> doe no more my ſonnes: and ſo it commeth to paſſe that when the Magiſtrate will not execute iuſtice, nor puniſh ſinne, to remooue euill from the land, God entreth for default of iuſtice, and ſeuerely puniſheth the whole common-wealth. How hatefull a gaine is this before the Lord: how filthy a lucre before good men? is it not the price of blood, which is the gaine of him who betrayeth the ſtate? the like miſchiefe ſometimes befalleth, when the Magiſtrate is indulgent at the inſtance of friends, or kinred; ſuch pleas are ſo common, that it is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing rare to obſerue that malefactor, who hath not ſome vncle, brother, couſen, or friend to ſtand vp an
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:16134:12"/>earneſt aduocate for his allies or cuſtomers impunity. What iuſtice, what feare of God is this? Or if iuſtice be impartially done, the vniuſt delinquents will doe their worſt ſpights, that the rare man, who without feare, fauour, or reſpect of filthy gaine, executeth iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice ſhall be vndone, for they will withdraw their cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes, becauſe the good man would not conniue and ſell them iuſtice, which they wickedly ſuppoſe as mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chantable as any wares, and a kind of vailes and due, vpon occaſions belonging to cuſtomers.</p>
            <p>It is time to conclude: Brethren, I am not ignorant of the cenſures the laſt election paſſed vpon me, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I did not after this manner, and according to the cuſtome of this place and time aduiſe you, but preached on another more generall ſubiect: I could haue anſwered then, how much it grieued mee, to heare ſome (too great a ſumme) crying like thoſe Iſraelites to <hi>Ieremy, Pray for vs vnto the Lord</hi>—<hi>that the Lord thy God may ſhew vs the way wherein wee are to walke, and the thing that we may do:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier. 42.2.3.</hi> Verba quidem pi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tatis plena: ſed verbis non conſo nant o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>opera. Theod. inter, in <hi>Ier. 42<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi>
               </note> yet intended not, what euer was preached, to follow (I will not ſay one word, but not) all. Words full of piety, but workes not conſonant to thoſe words: they did well to deſire to heare, but it is not well when that was all, and no practiſe followed. But now I ſay I haue better hope of you: and therefore aduiſe you againe, take heed that you now doe all, that you be not worthily retaxed, in that you onely call for that word, which you will not follow: be not like thoſe wicked Leuites, who com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to their conſecration made ſhew of ſanctifying hands, f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>et, and cares, but contrary to the ſanctitie of their order neuer cared more for the ſubſtance: ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour your authority as you are honoured by it, eclipſe</p>
            <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
